Guide to the Jules Weinstein Papers MC 210
New York University Archives
Jules Weinstein Papers
Bulk, 1951-1952
1939-1954
MC 210
New York University Archives
1.0 linear feet
The Jules Weinstein Papers include correspondence, published articles, and lecture notes by Dr. Jules Weinstein, whose academic and professional interests bridged the fields of dentistry and hypnosis.
Weinstein, Jules
Arrangement
Archives staff preserved original order when arranging this collection; with a few exceptions, it is arranged chronologically. Materials were removed from their original binder and placed into file folders.
The files are grouped into a single series.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains various papers concerning Jules Weinstein’s career between the years 1939 and 1954. Although it consists mostly of correspondence, it includes other materials as well, including journal articles and lecture notes. The two books included in this collection were not written solely by Weinstein, but they do include articles written by him and references to his work.
Biography of Jules Weinstein
Jules Weinstein, D.D.S., graduated from the New York College of Dentistry (later the New York University College of Dentistry) in 1924. Motivated by his studies of hypnosis during the 1930s and a strong belief that hypnosis would help to improve the experience of dental patients, Weinstein attempted to establish a place for hypnosis in the daily practice of dentistry. He lectured at New York University in the early 1950s on the application of hypnosis to dentistry.
During his thirty-year career at Harlem Hospital, he served as a member of the N.Y.C. Dental Society (First District), the Society for Clinical and Experimental Hypnosis, and the New York Academy of Sciences, as well as an advisor and founding member of the American Hypnodontic Society.
He wrote several articles on hypnosis in Dental Concepts and the British Journal of Hypnosis in Medicine. Weinstein also contributed to the book Medical Hypnosis, edited by Dr. Jerome Schenck. Additionally, he taught a post-graduate course entitled "An Introduction to Hypnosis in Dentistry" at the Bronx County Dental Society.
Dr. Weinstein died on July 27, 1954, after devoting his life toward research in and advocacy for the practice of hypnosis in medicine and dentistry.
Following Dr. Weinstein's death, the American Hypnodontic Society established the Jules Weinstein Annual Award for Leadership in Medical Dental Hypnosis. The first recipient was Dr. Aaron Moss in 1961.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Provenance
The collection was donated to New York University by Dr. Weinstein's granddaughter, Pamela Lerman, in 2007.
New York University.; Society for Clinical and Experimental Hypnosis (U.S.).; Weinstein, Jules; Books.; Bronx County (N.Y.).; Correspondence.; Dentistry.; Harlem Hospital Center (New York, N.Y.); Hypnotism.; Letters.
- Series I: Jules Weinstein Papers
  - Biography - Jules H. Weinstein, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Announcement of New York University - Periodontia Post-Graduate Symposium "Hypnosis in Dentistry" April 28, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Plans for Organization - Society for Advancement of Scientific Hypnotism, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter from Dr. Aaron Moss, Aug 31, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Harold J. Sloan (American Society for the Advancement of Hypnodontics), November 1, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Celestine S. Faber (New York State Dental Journal), January 30, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Charles F. Bodecker (New York State Dental Journal), February 17, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Editors of N.J. Journals of Dentistry, March 3, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. Walter Hyde to Dr. Aaron Moss, March 23, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. Charles Harper, (N.J. State Dental Society) to Dr. Aaron Moss, April 3, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. Charles Harper, April 9, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Harold Sloan, April 11, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter, Unclear Signature, April 11, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from J.B. Rhine (Parapsychology Department of Duke University), December 29, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from J.B. Rhine, April 7, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. Jerome Schenck (Author of Hypnosis in Modern Medicine), March 5, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from J.B. Rhine, April 7, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. Alfred H. Schilling, April 17, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. John Steponaitis (Chairman of the Executive Board, Waterbury Dental Society), July 26, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Dr. John Steponaitis, July 29, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Dr. John Steponaitis, August 13, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter from Dr. John Steponaitis, August 26, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Time Article "The Uses of Hypnosos," March 30, 1953 (Printed off Internet, January 6, 2007) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bulletin of the Tenth District Dental Society, March 1949, Volume I, Number 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter from Dr. George Goldsmith (Bronx County Dental Society), March 23, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Hypnosis in dentistry: A Graduate Course" (Notes), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "A Message to Every Dental Patient from the American Society for the Advancement of Hypnodontics" (by J.H. Weinstein), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Hypnotism in Dentistry, Part I" by Jules Weinstein, Dental Concepts, July 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Hypnotism in Dentistry, Part II" by Jules Weinstein, Dental Concepts, October 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hypnosis, Volume II, Number 4, October 1954 (Cover and Page 250), 1954-1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The British Journal of Medical Hypnotism, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Postcard invitations to lectures on hypnosis in dentistry by Dr. Weinstein and other members of the American Hypnodontic Society, 1938-1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photocopied certificates, 1924-1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Moss, Aaron A: Hypnodontics, or Hypnosis in Dentistry, 1952 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Schenck, Jerome M., ed.: Hypnosis in Modern Medicine, 1953 (Box 1, Item 2)